<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January XVI, 1675/6 by Roger Hayward.</title>
            <author>Hayward, Roger, 1639-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08951800</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08951800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1286:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January XVI, 1675/6 by Roger Hayward.</title>
                  <author>Hayward, Roger, 1639-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Basset,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, January <hi>xvj.</hi> 1675/6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ROGER HAYWARD,</hi> D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to HIS MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Baſſet,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>George,</hi> near St. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church, in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42086:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING.</head>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> in the 3d chapter of his Propheſie and the <hi>14th</hi> verſe, complains thus of the Jews: <q>
                  <hi>Ye have ſaid it is vain to ſerve God, and what profit is there that we have kept his ordinance?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Wiſdom and Goodneſs do not delight to exact thoſe ſervices, which are neither for the advantage of the impoſer nor obſerver, and when power enforces ſuch it renders them and it ſelf irkſom and tedious: Since <hi>the righteouſneſs of men cannot profit their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> we cannot reaſonably think He ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42086:3"/>enjoyn them any thing, which it is not their advantage to obſerve: Were His Commandments fruitleſs, they would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably prevent that cheerful obedience they do require, by ſtifling thoſe hopes that ſhould inſpire it; ſome few <hi>ſuperſtitious Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers,</hi> they might gain upon, <hi>Lovers</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> they would have none; <hi>to labour for the wind which ſatisfieth not,</hi> would chill the warmeſt affections, and force the humbleſt heart to complain as thoſe in my <hi>Text</hi> do.</p>
            <p>Of whom I have only this to note, when lately they ſate by the waters of <hi>Babylon</hi> they wept when they remembred <hi>Sion,</hi> and their language then no doubt was, <hi>O how amiable are thy dwellings, thou Lord of hoſts! one day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand!</hi> And now through the mercies of God they are there: But ſcarce was the Altar warm with the Sacrifice, but the <hi>vows</hi> and the <hi>tears</hi> they had offer'd for the Houſe of God when ſhe lay in the duſt, are turned into <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> now ſhe is in her glory; and they talk at ſuch a rate, as if they had never been, either in <hi>Babylon</hi> or in the <hi>Temple; Your words have been ſtout againſt me,</hi> verſe the <hi>13th;</hi> ſtout indeed, for,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42086:3"/> Ye have ſaid it is vain to ſerve God, and what profit is there that we have kept his ordinance?</q>
            <p>A Bold charge! that the Service of God was a ſtale uſeleſs device, an unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable impoſition on their labour and time, their Folds and their Granaries were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptied, their buſineſs and pleaſures interrupted, their ſpirits and wits pall'd, and they nothing advantag'd by it; and therefore in the next <hi>verſe</hi> they go on in the ſame ſtrain, <hi>the proud are happy, thoſe that work wickedneſs proſper, and thoſe that tempt God</hi> (by ſuch bold defiance, and never trouble themſelves with crowching before Him) <hi>are delivered:</hi> How happy was <hi>Harpalus,</hi> who never was at the charge of a grain of Incenſe on the Gods? I would this language were as obſolete as 'tis truly barbarous! and that there were none that gloried in it as a brave and lofty Idiom! But though there were none that publickly avowed, or ſecretly thought the Service of the <hi>Lord of Lords</hi> is uſeleſs; yet ſince our evil luſts are continually endeavouring (with ſo much ſucceſs) to make it ſo, I hope it will not be loſt time (on both
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42086:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42086:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42086:5"/>accompts) to juſtifie the wiſdom of our being here; and ſhew, that we are no where em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on a better accompt, than in the <hi>Courts of the Lord's Houſe,</hi> and that he never requir'd it of us <hi>to ſeek his face in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in order to it, I hope I may take the <hi>Being of a God,</hi> and the <hi>right of His ſervice,</hi> for granted, and if any in the mad hurry of their luſts deny the one, or the other, I would only deſire to know of them, how they came by their own Beings; and what title they can ſhew to any ſervice they expect, which is not meerly of others courteſie, and may not ſoon be cut off, if there be none due to God.</p>
            <p>I have then no more to do, but to declare,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What the <hi>Service</hi> here meant is.</item>
               <item>2. What the certain profits of it are.</item>
               <item>3. What are the cauſes of that <hi>vanity</hi> men are ſo ready to charge it with.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſenſe of the Divine Perfections naturally ſeizes us with <hi>admiration,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> (if our guilt interpoſe not, to turn the <hi>light of his countenance</hi> into a <hi>conſuming fire</hi>) ſoon grows into the higheſt <hi>veneration</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> which is the principal, the eternal <hi>ſervice</hi> of God, which (if it be not toil'd and weakened by our worldly luſts) cannot lye cloyſter d in our breaſts, but muſt, by its mighty force, break out into that <hi>lowly homage</hi> and <hi>ready obedience,</hi> which are the neceſſary products of it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42086:5"/>and the other <hi>ſervices</hi> that we owe him: The firſt of theſe <hi>(his worſhip)</hi> is the ſubject of the Text, as the whole ſcope of the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſhews, which is to regulate thoſe abuſes, to correct that Heatheniſm, which ſtole with them out of the <hi>Captivity</hi> into the <hi>ſecond Temple:</hi> This being a Duty we owe to Him, firſt as his Creatures, then as ſinful and miſerable, but not paſt hope, conſiſts of thoſe acts which are the cleareſt acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our entire <hi>dependance on his goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſubjection to his authority,</hi> ſuch are our humble <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions, prayers, praiſes,</hi> and <hi>meek receiving his laws,</hi> for what other ſolemn recognition of our honour of Him can we make, than the devoting our ſelves to his <hi>Mercy</hi> and his <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Sacrifice, mention'd in the Text, ſeems indeed to have been the whole of the Jewiſh <hi>Temple Service,</hi> but if we obſerve, from the Prophets, the low accompt God made of it, we muſt conclude, that (what antiquity ſoever it boaſt) it was but the <hi>shadow</hi> of this <hi>reaſonable ſervice;</hi> What deſigned proſpect it had (as a Type or viſible Prophecy) on the <hi>Sacrifice of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Body,</hi> I do not enquire, ſince there is not any notice taken of it by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Laws, to excite the Peoples Faith or Devotion;
<note place="margin">Jer. 7.23. Pſal. 50.5.</note> but that (beſides that obedience which it chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) it was an oblation of the Offerer himſelf, by his repreſentative, to God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42086:6"/>as <hi>Philo</hi> deſcribes it, viſible confeſſions, prayers, and praiſes, is ſo obvious a meaning of it, that none can miſs or doubt of; nor was this way of Worſhip meerly trifling and ſcenical, but (if we conſider the time, the place, the temper of that People) neceſſary to ſave them from falling into the tempting Idolatries of the Nations, 'till ſuch time as the World was prepared for the <hi>Holy Offering</hi> foretold in the 1. chapter, 11. verſe, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Apol. 2.</note> as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> renders it,
<note place="margin">Con. <hi>Marc.</hi> c. 22.</note> 
               <hi>mundities ſacrificorum,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the ſacrifices of prayer, praiſes, and a broken and contrite Spirit.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 50.14, 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is that <hi>true ſpiritual</hi> Worſhip our <hi>Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> hath eſtabliſh'd, having ſcattered thoſe clouds of ſmoke, aſhes, and blood, that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Temple, by the clear diſcoveries of Gods Will, and the doubts and fears which darkned Mens Souls, by the greateſt encouragements of his Spirit to aſſiſt, and Himſelf to intercede for them; and thoſe two poſitive Rites he hath ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added to it, are only the early dedication, and frequent rendition of our ſelves to God, ratified by the uſual Solemnities of Baptizing and Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, which he conſecrated to the remembrance of the two greateſt Bleſſings, <hi>His Spirit,</hi> and <hi>His Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which it appears, how neceſſary the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Goſpel was to our comfortable and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42086:6"/>acceptable Service of God; had he not ſhown us Himſelf by his Son, told us how, and in what Name we are to approach Him, what we are to ask of Him, and what will pleaſe Him, we muſt have wandred in the dark after the Heathens, multiplied our Gods and our Altars, and at length, being tired with a vain ſearch, have rear'd one to the <hi>unknown God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, as for thoſe Rites and Modes Men are ſo fierce againſt, would they would believe us when we plainly avow, they are no parts of the Chriſtian Worſhip, but ſince the Goſpel (not meant for a <hi>ritual</hi> but <hi>rule of righteouſneſs</hi>) gives not one direct Precept for any the moſt material Circumſtance in it, and confuſion and diſorder muſt, without miracles, expoſe and ruin it, therefore it is neceſſary, that ſome ſhould be appointed and obſerved: And thoſe that are ſcared from the Service of God, by every little Mode in it that is not of Divine inſtitution, muſt leave, not this but all Churches, and finally fall out with their own moſt careful Addreſſes to God; ſo uneaſie to it ſelf, as well as others, is this ſuperſtitious fear of offending God by ſuch little things, as do not deſerve his moſt wiſe and glorious Anger, yea ſo unfriendly to the very Service it ſelf hath it prov'd, that I fear it hath emboldened too many, that are more hardy, to lay it by wholly, as a nice and troubleſome, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42086:7"/>to trifle with it as an indifferent thing, and made it too neceſſary for us to prove, that <hi>'tis not in vain for us to ſerve God,</hi> which is the next thing I am to do.</p>
            <p>As our inward Honour is the Principle of our outward Service, ſo is this Service the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Honour, and ſo the whole proof will lye upon this Enquiry, What real benefit redounds to our Souls, and to the World, by the Reverence of God upheld therein? We dare not think ſo meanly of Him, as that He deſigns any advantage to Himſelf by it; if we think the glory He requires of us by it is any new acceſſion to Him, or any thing more than the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Goodneſs to us, under the pretence of adoring Him, we advance our ſelves, as if we with our hands lift up, with our <hi>Halelujahs,</hi> did ſupport his Throne.</p>
            <p>Again, that his Service is uſeful to procure the pardon of our ſins, the care of his Providence, and Eternal Life we are all aſſur'd, but who is ſo fooliſh as to think, that there is any natural virtue in our breath, which grows cold upon our lips, to draw down theſe Heavenly Influences? or ſo immodeſt to preſume, that theſe great favours are the juſt purchaſe of a few good words, a little patient attendance, and lowly behaviour? It remains then, that the great profit of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is not in any effects or impreſſions it makes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42086:7"/>upon God, <hi>with whom is no ſhadow of change,</hi> but in thoſe diſpoſitions it begets in us, whereby we are fitted for the Divine Bounty; therefore the firſt and immediate benefit of it is to our Souls, and the good influence it hath upon them, is to frame them to the Divine Likeneſs.</p>
            <p>'Twas the ſenſe of the beſt Heathens; that the imitation of God is the beſt Worſhip of Him, that it is the proper reſult of it, <hi>if we do not flatter with our lips,</hi> is evident, becauſe the true venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any thing, transforms all the thoughts and deſires into its reſemblance,
<note place="margin">2 Cor.3.18.</note> 
               <hi>beholding the glory of God we are changed into the ſame image;</hi> which Image is not a dead Idol of the Brain, the phantaſtick wealth of that wild <hi>Athenian,</hi> who told all the Ships in the Haven for his own, but vital Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs,</hi> which are the only participation of the Divine Nature we are capable of. Behold then the Treaſures of the Temple! for ſure all the Graces of Gods Spirit, and all thoſe Divine and Heavenly Diſpoſitions, that enlarge, ſtrengthen, and adorn the Spirit of a Man, that make it equal to all good actions and evil accidents, that fit him to be a God to others, a Heaven to himſelf, and a Friend to his God, do amount to no contemptible ſtore: Thoſe that will allow Virtue to be no more than ſome common Matter, ſtamp'd with Authority, do by that grant it to be currant Coin, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42086:8"/>'tis hard for any to be in earneſt and ſay, that thoſe Excellencies which have civilized the World, and ſupport Societies, which put Men in the firmeſt poſſeſſion of their own and one anothers Hearts, which all Men admire, and the worſt counterfeit, ſhould not be worth the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after.</p>
            <p>To ſhew how effectual an Inſtrument the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is to the obtaining of them, I ſhall not inſiſt upon the Divine Appointment, which yet, were it but <hi>clay</hi> and <hi>ſpittle,</hi> were enough to juſtifie its ſufficiency, for we live in an Age, wherein not all other only, but even the Divine Authority is ſuſpected, and to quote the Text is judged by ſome as unconcluding in Divinity, as by others in Philoſophy. Nor will I urge the approbation of thoſe, who have faithfully tryed it, and by its Miniſtery arriv'd to be great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Goodneſs, and the vicious Habits and Lives of thoſe that deſpiſe and neglect it: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this may be evaded, yet the force of theſe plain Conſiderations may, I hope, <hi>by Gods grace,</hi> make it undeniable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Reverence of God</hi> is the only firm Foundation to build a true and ſtable Goodneſs on: The Laws of Nature, by that mixture of Natures that is in us, are ſo eaſie to be miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, confounded, and ſhaken, that the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture muſt needs be tottering that is built upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42086:8"/>them; and how faint and flexible muſt all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward engagements to it be, when a more cogent inconvenience preſſes it, ſo that theſe leave it a meer chance thing, juſt as circumſtances fall out, whether there be any obligation to it or no: But the <hi>Reverence</hi> of the <hi>Great God</hi> preſerves it ever firm and inviolable, over-awes all powers that may aſſault it, and makes the ſtrongeſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it to be its greateſt glory;<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Walk before me</hi> (ſays God to <hi>Abraham</hi>) <hi>and be perfect.</hi> But how can this Reverence be preſerved in our hearts, without frequent and ſolemn attendance and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Him, any more than the Authority of a King, without his Courts of Juſtice and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The ſtrongeſt habits, yea thoſe natural affections, that are moſt deeply engrav'd on our hearts, wear away gradually by diſuſe and ſtrangeneſs: The Principles of Reaſon, Conſent of Nations, Order and Beauty of the Univerſe, may keep alive the Belief of his Being; but theſe (without the frequent and ſolemn <hi>proclamation of his Will,</hi> and <hi>invocation of his Name</hi>) are but as the dead Records of a Chronicle or Calendar, which will no better keep up the Honour of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, than they do the Wonders of the Creation. Soon would the incurſions of worldly vanities, ſeconded with our own ſenſual luſts, bear down that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Clem. Alex.</note> that natural inclination we have to God, and all the Characters he hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42086:9"/>left of Himſelf in our Conſcience, or in the Creation, if they were not often quickened and refreſhed by the moſt devout remembrances; and that deep <hi>forgetfulneſs of God</hi> (which we call A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm) is not born with, nor ſuddenly ſeizes upon any, but creeps upon them inſenſibly, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe of his Service.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſuppoſing we could preſerve the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God without it, yet neither can this, or any other Principle make us good, without his aſſiſtance to make it preſent and powerful. This is a Truth, which the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the worſt Men ſeals, for why elſe do they flye to Nature, Neceſſity, and Impoſſibility, to be their Compurgators? And the <hi>Confeſsions</hi> of the beſt do avow, who finding the greateſt difficulty to be rooted in themſelves, cry out with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>Oh wretched men that we are who ſhall deliver us!</hi> Yea, and thoſe that never heard of the <hi>mighty Wind on Pentecoſte,</hi> yet would not grant, that any could be excellent, <hi>ſine afflatu divino,</hi> ſo the Orator; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo <hi>Hierocles.</hi> And however Men may pride themſelves in their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and think their Souls can mend themſelves when they liſt, yet they dare not truſt their Bodies, when ſick and languiſhing, to the weak remains of life and ſtrength, to effect their own recovery; <hi>Ariſe, take up thy bed and walk,</hi> would be a ſcornful taunt from any Mouth but our Makers; ſome new Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42086:9"/>and Succours they are forc'd to flye to, to joyn with and reinforce their poor baffled powers, for what can they do, when they themſelves are oppreſt and out of order? There is indeed an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſelf-moving power in the Soul, which can never be loſt, there is an Elatery, a <hi>motus reſtitutionis,</hi> an endeavour to Goodneſs in the Conſcience, which cannot be extinguiſhed; but when this power is corrupted, when this ſpring is ruſted, and a mighty weight lyes upon it, what weak effects are we to expect from it? When the <hi>light within us is darkneſs,</hi> when reaſon it ſelf (the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) hath tamely given up its Sovereignty, to be <hi>led captive by divers luſts,</hi> how can it alone bring about its reſtauration?</p>
            <p>And now, if the one neceſſity of the Divine Aſſiſtance be admitted, I know not how the other of humble applications to Him can mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly be denied. Gods Grace deſcends not like the common Bleſſings of the Light and Showers, whether Men deſire it or no, it were not grace but force, not aſſiſtance but violence, were it not earneſtly and humbly ſought;<note place="margin">Mat. 7.7</note> 
               <hi>Ask and ye ſhall have, ſeek and ye ſhall find.</hi> And of the ſucceſs of this there can be no doubt, if we conſider in the next place,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The direct propriety our Worſhip of God hath to make us good: There are but two ways, without miracle, whereby we may ever hope it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42086:10"/>by being clearly inſtructed, and ſufficiently obliged and encouraged to it, whatſoever doth theſe doth edifie, all elſe is but empty noiſe and rituality. Now what clearer accompts of Goodneſs can we deſire, than thoſe we have from the Laws and Life of Goodneſs it ſelf, which took a Body and dwelt among us? and what ſtronger bonds could Wiſdom and Love heve knit, than thoſe of Duty and Intereſt, of Gratitude and Hope, of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Succeſs? where our Maker intreats, our Saviour bleeds, his Spirit and our Conſciences contend with us, where his terrours do beſet us, his bowels of compaſſion yern towards us, and the Heavens are open'd before us, how is it poſſible we break through all to our ruin? Theſe are the engagements God lays on us in his Worſhip, but we are not meerly paſſive there, we come not to be enchanted and chained, but to bind all theſe upon our ſelves by our own act and deed; when we <hi>confeſs,</hi> we do not tell a ſad ſtory, but abjure our iniquities before God, his Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Men; when we <hi>pray,</hi> we do not plead or argue with God, but we humbly declare our purpoſes, and our requeſts, if they are ſerious, become our vows; when we <hi>praiſe</hi> him, we cauſe not our voices to be heard on high, but we humbly breath out our hearts to him, having no greater preſent for his Love. Laſtly, when we receive the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> we devote our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42086:10"/>ſelves to Him with all the ſolemnities of fealty and friendſhip, and how ſtupendious ſoever a miſery ſome have made of that Act of Worſhip, (by ſtraining the holy Expreſſions of the Fathers into an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of it) yet in this our plain deſpis'd notion, 'tis an excellent Inſtrument of uniting us to the <hi>Holy Jeſus in ſpirit,</hi> and if we believe Him, <hi>the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6.63.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly, the ſumm of all that Goodneſs, that can make us acceptable to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> is <hi>Humility, Charity,</hi> and <hi>purity of Spirit.</hi> For the firſt, Men never ſee themſelves in a true light (thoſe eſpecially who have few or none ſuperiour to them upon Earth) but when they <hi>ſtand in His Preſence,</hi> there the ſhadows flye away, and they (as <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>ſee and abhor themſelves in duſt and aſhes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 42.5, 6.</note> there <hi>men of all degrees are found to be lighter than vanity.</hi> How great improvement Charity gains by it, will be the next enquiry: But how is it poſſible, that we, who live in continual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with the World (chiefly thoſe who are under no reſtraints of want or fear) ſhould keep our ſelves <hi>undefiled,</hi> without thoſe ſolemn retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from it, whereby we may diſintangle our Minds from the Cares and Pleaſures of it, and by <hi>taſting the good things of the world to come,</hi> correct the keenneſs of our Appetites to this?</p>
            <p>'Tis to be expected, that ſome ſhould reply to this Diſcourſe, Hath the <hi>Temple</hi> then mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliz'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42086:11"/>all Goodneſs? Is Grace appropriated only to the <hi>Prieſts Lips?</hi> Can Reaſon do nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe dull Formalities? Were not <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> as fruitful of happy Spirits, as <hi>the City that was watered with the River of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> that <hi>we poor earthen Veſſels</hi> ſhould ever arrogate any power over the <hi>Treaſures</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us! And would to God all the Courts of Princes, the Seats of Juſtice, and Schools of Learning, were holy as the <hi>Courts of the Lords Houſe!</hi> But if many of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the beſt natural diſpoſitions, of the ſtrongeſt faculties, and of the greateſt advantages of education and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, do yet fall ſhort of thoſe Virtues that may thence be expected, there is no reaſon to be given for it, but their neglects of the Miniſtery of Religion; and by this God lets the World ſee, that He is not to be left out in a buſineſs that ſo wholly depends upon Him, that whoſoever <hi>plants or waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>He alone muſt give the increaſe.</hi> 'Tis no doubt, but the Capitol in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Schools at <hi>Athens,</hi> had ſome Souls in them, not commonly to be match'd in our beſt Oratories, but we find none ſuch, who had not a ſtrong ſenſe of, and awful regard to the Deity, though their Notions and Worſhip run muddy and foul, falling into the Countrey ſtream; and if they were better with leſs help than we, the more only is our blame: Let us not charge the <hi>Vineyard
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42086:11"/>of Gods own planting</hi> for a barren Soil, ſince the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> hath been ſo fruitful.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But this is not all the benefit we gain by our <hi>Service of God;</hi> when the World is well awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened out of its enthuſiaſtick ſlumber and giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Men will ſee that <hi>Religion</hi> was not ſhorn for a Recluſe to the <hi>Church,</hi> but whatever is good for the Souls, is likewiſe ſo for the Societies of Men: Now the Worſhip of God being ſo fit (as I have ſhown) to beget in us thoſe diſpoſitions, which are (not the Ornaments of a Cloyſter, but the Pillars of the Earth, and) as neceſſary to the very Being of a Society, as the Air they breath in, or the Ground they tread on, doth on that ſcore turn to a vaſt accompt: Upon which the wiſeſt Heathens have declared it to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Plut.</note> But of this I ſhall give but two Inſtances, but they are ſuch, wherein the peace and proſperity of Men is wholly bound.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A cheerful ſubmiſsion and regard to their ſeveral Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A mutual confidence in one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How mean and humble ſoever <hi>Piety</hi> looks, though it dazles not the Eyes as ſpendour, nor terrifies the Fancy as power doth, yet it arreſts the Heart with a more irreſiſtible force than either; for it ſlakes that envy, tames that ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs, and layes thoſe jealouſies, which thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42086:12"/>are apt to raiſe, and haunt uneaſie minds: For who will grudge to ſubmit to, fear any evil from, or dare any evil to him, that is a lover and beloved of his God? So the Authority of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Prieſts, Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> is at once ſweetened and reinforc'd. Thus the Heathens deſcents of their Rulers from their Gods, their frequent inſpirations by, and familiar converſes with them, were not the contrivance of their Fancy, but their Wiſdom: 'Twas the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> that ſerved both the Capitol and the Camp, whetted their Wits and their Swords, made them ſtrong Laws, won them rich Provinces, and two of the wideſt Empires now in the World ſtand upon the Credit of a <hi>Prophet</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> his continual Addreſſes to God, awed that ſtubborn People, as much as his powerful Rod, that <hi>turned the hard Rock into a Spring of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> But we need not go ſo far, we our ſelves have ſufficiently felt the deep impreſſions of a <hi>pretended devotion,</hi> when a days faſting (or <hi>ſeeking God</hi>) hath more enraged Men to the ſpoil, than the greateſt largeſs could. And though the moſt barbarous uſage of <hi>the moſt Pious King,</hi> may ſeem to weaken the ſecurity of <hi>Religion,</hi> yet we muſt remember, that there were a People, from whoſe fury the real Divinity of our Saviour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Legions of Angels, could not defend Him. But I hope there are none among us ſo far
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42086:12"/>relaps'd, whom after ſo much mercy, an equal Piety would not recover and overcome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Worſhip of God</hi> begets a good confidence among Men: Did it no more than make them known and familiar to each other, and remove that ſtrangeneſs which begets ſuſpicion, it were not quite contemptible; but this is the leaſt of its virtue. Freedom of converſe is the beſt means to aſſure Men of each other, they that commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their thoughts and purpoſes exchange minds, and give the greateſt mutual hoſtages they can. Now if our Tongues keep pace with our Service, and our Hearts with them, there is none more intimate, though not ſo particular, converſation as here, where, if we mark what we ſay, we joyntly diſcover our weightieſt thoughts, our higheſt deſigns, our neareſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, yea, ſo ingenuous and free we are, as not to diſſemble our very neceſſities and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: All this we do, or we do nothing, when we <hi>confeſs</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> together; and to hatch us yet cloſer, our Prayers are Vows of Charity, when we lift up our hands to Heaven, we ſtrike them with each other, for we beg Gods compaſſion and mercies, on condition of our own; and what is all we come to hear, but ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſuch Examples of Love and good will, as will link us together, either in <hi>love</hi> or <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> But if we go higher, to the <hi>Feaſt of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42086:13"/>there are all thoſe endearments of <hi>bleeding love,</hi> and <hi>flowing plenty,</hi> which may tame and win the fierceſt Natures; in all which <hi>(behold and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der!)</hi> the <hi>God of Love and Peace</hi> Himſelf becomes a <hi>Mediator</hi> betwixt us, uſing all the motives of his Authority and Love, to lay our quarrelſom luſts, and unite us in an everlaſting friendſhip. But if our <hi>Service</hi> reach not the perfection of its deſign, yet this great good it uſually doth, it begets a good opinion of Mens Conſciences, which is the beſt hold they can have of each other; ſo the <hi>Eaſterns</hi> ratified their Covenants with Sacrifice, and the fouleſt Character of <hi>Doeg</hi>'s Treachery to <hi>David</hi> was,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.14.</note> that <hi>they took ſweet counſel together, and went into the Houſe of God like friends.</hi> And now, if our worſhipping God together proves not ſo ſtrong a cement of friendſhip as trading, or fighting, or drinking together, it is becauſe we make our <hi>gain,</hi> our <hi>glory,</hi> and our <hi>belly our God,</hi> in that the mediation of theſe is more powerful with us, than that of our <hi>great God and Saviour.</hi> Laſtly, 'tis to be hoped, that (after ſo ſad experience) none will lay the charge of thoſe Contentions and Wars, that have waſted the Church, at her doors; 'tis not <hi>Gods Service,</hi> but the ſervice of Mens <hi>luſts</hi> and <hi>paſsions</hi> (that for their better credit take that name) which hath done thoſe miſchiefs, but if the <hi>Religious Feuds</hi> have ſtill been (as is obſerved) the moſt fatal, it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42086:13"/>makes good the truth, for their <hi>Friendſhips</hi> have at the ſame time been moſt firm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, if at the foot of this accompt I add, that the <hi>Service of God</hi> fits us for his <hi>eternal viſion,</hi> it will (to us that hope and pray for that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) be judged very profitable; ſo cloſely are the Intereſts of both Worlds connected, that whatever diſpoſes us to live <hi>well</hi> and <hi>happily</hi> here, fits us likewiſe for <hi>life eternal;</hi> for neither will our Natures be otherwiſe changed, than from the bondage of our <hi>corruptible bodies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> nor our Service, than from thoſe <hi>rudiments of this world, prayer</hi> and <hi>penitence,</hi> which our preſent ſinful and neceſſitous ſtate of Pilgrimage requires; the Bleſſed Angels ever <hi>hearken to the Voice of his Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.20</note> and <hi>never ceaſe to give glory and honour to God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 4.8.</note> Mens future portions will not be aſſign'd them according to their <hi>hopes,</hi> but their <hi>habits;</hi> they therefore that have ſpent all their days in the <hi>Tents of wickedneſs,</hi> whoſe <hi>tongues have been full of curſing and bitterneſs,</hi> whoſe hands have never been lift up but to <hi>violence</hi> or <hi>vanity,</hi> without ſome more ſudden, violent, and miraculous change, than they have any ground to hope for, would be utterly incapable to be happy in that Society, in thoſe Employments, to which they have been ſo wholly eſtranged. But how eaſie, how pleaſant will our paſſage be, from the <hi>Courts of Gods Houſe</hi> to <hi>the Holy of Holies?</hi> How ready, how joyful ſhall we be, to joyn
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42086:14"/>with the Heavenly Quire in their <hi>Hallelujahs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus uſeful it is to ſerve God, to our <hi>Souls,</hi> to our <hi>Societies,</hi> to our <hi>Hopes of Heaven;</hi> and yet it is too ſadly true, that too many are neither the fitter to live nor to dye for it, and that's the matter of the laſt Enquiry, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How it becomes ſo vain, it muſt be from one of theſe Cauſes:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That Men miſapply it to a wrong end,</hi> or</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That they manage it a wrong way,</hi> either of which muſt needs render the beſt things uſeleſs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There are too many ſo groſs, as to think there is no profit but 20 <hi>per cent.</hi> nor gain but ready money. This was the <hi>Jews</hi> humour, who brought their Sacrifice as to a <hi>Market,</hi> not an <hi>Altar,</hi> and came to barter the Fleſh and Blood of their Beaſts for fair <hi>Harveſts</hi> and full <hi>Vintages,</hi> and when they miſſed, complained <hi>all was in vain.</hi> That the Service of God hath a friendly regard to worldly proſperity, is evident, becauſe it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines Men to be ſerious, engages them to be honeſt, diligent, and temperate in all things, and inſpires them with that calmneſs of mind, and comfortable truſt in Gods Providence, which are ſurer ways to proſperity, than all the little ſlights of the <hi>Mammoniſt;</hi> but if we expect more from it, we defeat it, and deceive our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42086:14"/>
            <p> Others, that would be more <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> put not their Devotion to that drudgery, which is fitter for the ſweat of their brows; all the gain they expect from it, is to have their Fancies a little refreſh'd, their Wits exerciſed, their Opinions, and perhaps their Luſts ſoothed, and (if it ſo happen) away go they, well ſatisfied, though indeed <hi>poor, and miſerable, and blind, and naked;</hi> but, if this be all their aim, they might have gain'd as much in the Fields or the Theatre. Great is that joy, and full of glory, that all pious Souls have in their Devotions; but 'tis not ſuch as is born of noiſe or art, and dyes with it, but that more ſolid and laſting, that ſprings from the ſenſe of Goodneſs entring like light and health into the Soul.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſome perhaps are ſo vain, as to hope by their Service to raiſe a mighty Intereſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and by their loud importunities, or more ſtudied addreſſes, to be able to tyre or charm the Almighty, to do what they will, without any regard to any impreſſions made on their own Spirits. What a wild conceit is this of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which is enough to ſpoil it, were it winged with the ardours of Angels? Can Men be ſerious, and think that their Confeſſions can inform Him of more than He knows of them? that their Petitions can direct Him what to do? or that their Language and Paſſions can overcome Him againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42086:15"/>his Will? No, no! we <hi>confeſs</hi> only to the melting down our own Iron necks, we <hi>pray</hi> to excite and engage our own ſtupid and falſe hearts, we <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede</hi> to enlarge our charity, we <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>laud</hi> Him to increaſe his love in us; ſo much as is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of our Service upon our ſelves, ſo much only is our gain; if this be not our aim, we only <hi>ſow the Wind, and may reap the Whirlwind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The other Cauſe of the vanity of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is our uſing it a wrong way. 'Tis too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with us to poſt it off (as a piece of <hi>Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice</hi>) to a Proxy, and to think we have nothing to do in it, but to lend an Eye, or an Ear, to make a dumb ſhew, or a formal noiſe. Were the Holy Offices of Religion ſome common vile drudgery, or ſome powerful Charms or Spells, they would not deſerve or need our thoughts; but they are of another nature, wiſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Inſtruments for our good, and therefore require an <hi>intent mind,</hi> and an <hi>honeſt and good heart,</hi> to make them effectual. If Men come before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand reſolved, that <hi>hearing they will not hear, nor conſider,</hi> though the <hi>Angels,</hi> or the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> would again deſcend, they would baffle their Miniſtery. The Ground we ſtand on is not ſo Holy, but if we do not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Pyth. Symb. Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>keep our feet when we come into the Houſe of God,</hi> we may return as impure as we came; nor is the Air ſo fine, as to cleanſe us from all pollution, by the meer ventilation of it;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42086:15"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> his Tabernacle, nor <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, (though they had the <hi>Shecinah,</hi> the Glory of the Lord filling them) could not hallow a careleſs Worſhipper: Did we negotiate our buſineſs, our Trade, with as little thoughtfulneſs as we pray and hear, our gains would come in but ſlowly; we need not indeed that ſubtilty, and thoſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in our dealings with God, as with Men, yet certainly He alone is not to be ſerved, nor our Souls only to be improved, without any thoughts or care for them. And indeed, how is it poſſible, that ſuch excellent Prayers, ſo often ſent up to the Throne of Grace, ſhould periſh in the Air? that all the powerful perſwaſives to Goodneſs, that Heaven and Earth afford, which ring continually in our Ears, ſhould never reach our Hearts? that having one Advocate within us to help our Infirmities, and another in Heaven to preſent our Services, yet they ſhould be ſtill ineffectual? It could not be, but that we only are inexorable, and will not hear our own Prayers; we are imperſwaſible, and will not believe our own ſelves, our own Conſciences: We <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>approve,</hi> and yet we <hi>reject</hi> the Counſels of God; we cry to God for <hi>mercy,</hi> and yet will have none upon our ſelves; we ask for <hi>grace,</hi> and yet will not take it when 'tis offered to us, or <hi>turn it into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs.</hi> Thus, whilſt we anticipate our latter end, and ſtand like Tombs in the Church, full
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42086:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42086:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42086:17"/>of uncleanneſs, what good can we expect? When the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> fell, but the beaſt liv'd in Men; when the <hi>incenſe</hi> aſcended, but their <hi>filthineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in their skirts;</hi> when the Air was filled, and every thing moved with their cryes, but their own inſenſate hearts; then had the Prophet reaſon to complain,<note place="margin">Jer. 7.4, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Ye truſt in lying words, ſaying, the Temple of the Lord; the Temple of the Lord, ye truſt in lying words which cannot profit;</hi> and 'tis no wonder to hear themſelves complain, <hi>It is in vain to ſerve God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now upon the whole we may conclude, 1. what a neceſſary connexion there is betwixt the Services of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> I pray it may never happen to theſe, as it hath done to others as near Allies (Faith and Good Works, Reaſon and Grace) to be put at odds, and both to loſe by a needleſs competition; and yet our practice bids too fair for putting a doctrinal difference betwixt theſe; why elſe do we offer God, an <hi>hour or two's</hi> attendance for a whole <hi>weeks</hi> licentiouſneſs, a few <hi>bows</hi> and <hi>Amens</hi> for a many high <hi>provocations?</hi> We run deeply in debt to his Juſtice, in confidence, that the next time we wait on Him in his Houſe, we ſhall clear all, and then, as if we had left Him our Debitor, we forbear not any thing our luſts do call for. Thus we make our Chriſtian Sabboth and Service <hi>a reſt from our ſins,</hi> but in the worſt ſenſe, that is, only a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42086:17"/>ſhort pauſe, to take breath and heart to purſue them with a greater reſolution. Were our <hi>God</hi> ſome <hi>Topical</hi> one, as thoſe of the <hi>Hills</hi> and <hi>Valleys</hi> of old, whoſe Authority were ſhut up within their Walls, then this might paſs for <hi>Worſhip,</hi> but whatever we call it, 'tis but a baſe and ſcornful Flattery, fit for an <hi>Idol that is nothing.</hi> God forbid we ſhould any of us ſerve our <hi>Friend,</hi> our <hi>Benefactor,</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> as we do <hi>our God!</hi> that is, come and ſtand demurely in his preſence, accuſe our ſelves and vow amendment; hear all he can promiſe or threaten to engage us to it, and immediately take every trifling occaſion to rebel againſt him. If we need not <hi>obey</hi> Him, why are we ſo fooliſh to <hi>worſhip</hi> Him? If we muſt <hi>worſhip</hi> Him, why are we ſo falſe to <hi>diſobey</hi> Him? Is his Being ſo <hi>glorious,</hi> to deſerve that; and are his Laws ſo <hi>contemptible,</hi> to endure this? We need not uſe ſo much <hi>ceremony</hi> to be wicked and miſerable: Let us take heed leſt He juſtly reward us for ſuch daring mockery, that is, <hi>laugh at our calamity,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.26, 27.</note> and mock when our fear cometh as deſolation, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction as a whirlwind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as our <hi>worſhip</hi> without <hi>obedience</hi> is vain, ſo our <hi>obedience</hi> without <hi>worſhip</hi> is impoſſible: We complain againſt the corrupt manners of the Age, and cry out,<note place="margin">Iſ. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>From the ſole of the feet even unto the head, there is no ſoundneſs in it, but wounds and bruiſes and putrifying ſores;</hi> and what do our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42086:18"/>complaints, but only fret and exaſperate? what can all our Arts do, but only palliate the Evil? How ſhall we be mended, whilſt our Souls are out of frame? and how ſhall we ever recover our <hi>ancient Virtues,</hi> without that <hi>ancient ſeriouſneſs in Religion,</hi> which hath ever been obſerved to be the particular <hi>Genius</hi> of this Nation, yea even then, when it fell infinitely ſhort of thoſe great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages it now enjoys? Can <hi>Virtue</hi> riſe out of the duſt, or <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ſpring out of the earth, or <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> grow out of our corrupt luſts? Can knowledge or reaſoning alone ſubdue thoſe evil habits, they have been ſo long uſed to abet and maintain? <hi>Mercies</hi> have made us wanton, and <hi>Judgments</hi> ſtupid, and we have been <hi>too miſerable,</hi> and are yet <hi>too happy</hi> to be mended, without the <hi>mighty grace of God.</hi> This then is the great, the fundamental Evil, the ſourſe of all the reſt, that we neglect or pervert the greateſt and only <hi>remedy</hi> he hath appointed for our <hi>cure,</hi> that we trifle with God in his Service, that ſhould procure thoſe ſuccours, without which we ſhall never be better; whilſt ſome Men make it their <hi>ſport,</hi> others their <hi>trade,</hi> ſome the matter of their <hi>contention,</hi> and ſome few the <hi>entertainment</hi> of their <hi>idle</hi> time: Whilſt we thus abuſe Gods counſel and aſſiſtance, what hope can remain for us? Were that breath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in <hi>hearty prayers,</hi> that is ſpent in <hi>fruitleſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42086:18"/>murmurings,</hi> did we uſe that thoughtfulneſs in our <hi>addreſſes to God,</hi> that we loſe in our vain <hi>contrivances,</hi> they would no doubt turn to a better accompt than they do: When we have wearied our ſelves with our <hi>loud complaints,</hi> and our <hi>little remedies,</hi> we may find at length, that <hi>'tis as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible to mend, as to make a World, or a Soul, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God.</hi> And however in the days of our <hi>proſperity</hi> we trifle with Him as an uſeleſs thing, without whom we can ſhift well enough,<note place="margin">Prov. 7.28.</note> yet <hi>when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon us,</hi> we ſhall, with much more earneſtneſs, but as little ſucceſs, <hi>call upon him, but he will not anſwer, ſeek him early, but ſhall not find him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> as the tormented Glutton in Hell (where there is a <hi>faith</hi> though <hi>trembling,</hi> a <hi>devotion</hi> though <hi>deſpairing</hi>) begg'd one drop of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but it could not be granted him. What help then are we to expect from theſe, who talk at the rate of thoſe in the <hi>Text,</hi> I mean not the wild <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> only, (whoſe zeal is as keen againſt <hi>Courts</hi> as <hi>Churches,</hi> were they not better guarded) but thoſe that would be the <hi>Reſtorers of Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Defenders of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of Nature,</hi> who would free the Countrey from the impoſtures of thoſe <hi>wily Craftſmen,</hi> who cry up this their <hi>Diana</hi> to get them utterance for their ſhrines. Whoſoever he be, that makes <hi>Gods Worſhip</hi> an Engin to keep up <hi>his own,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.4, 8.</note> 
               <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be that ſits in the Temple of God, to exalt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42086:19"/>himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> we pray, as the Apoſtle propheſieth, <hi>that God would deſtroy them with the ſpirit of his mouth.</hi> But ſure all Scripture is not <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> nor all <hi>houſes of prayer</hi> become <hi>dens of thieves;</hi> were there any <hi>cloſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> any <hi>ſecret adyta,</hi> any pretences to <hi>inſpirations</hi> or <hi>miraculous powers,</hi> in our Worſhip, then they might ſuſpect ſome juggling; but when every part and paſſage is plain and open (as the Book that contains it) to the meaneſt Worſhipper, what is it they can be jealous of? And would they would conſider, e're they cry <hi>down with it, even to the ground,</hi> whither <hi>Schools,</hi> and <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Courts,</hi> do not lean on the ſame Foundation! Were the Names of Virtue and Goodneſs, were Mens own Nature, and the Happineſs of the World, truly dear to them, the Names of the <hi>Great God</hi> the <hi>Maker of the World, Father of Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Fountain of Goodneſs,</hi> and of the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Reſtorer</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> of them, would be highly venerable to them, and all the Offices of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to them would be the moſt wiſe and ſerious actions of their life. How much then do they deſerve the care and love of us all! thoſe eſpecially, who have not only the Government of Men, but the higheſt, the tendereſt Truſt imaginable (greater than that of <hi>Durandus</hi> his Angels) committed to their charge;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bak.</hi> Chron. <hi>Canutus.</hi>
               </note> who though they cannot with their foot <hi>ſtop the ſwelling Tide,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42086:19"/>yet by their <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>tongue</hi> may check the <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flood</hi> of <hi>profaneneſs</hi> and <hi>barbariſm,</hi> and by Gods bleſſing ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt go no further,</hi> and ſo help to ſave an Age of Souls, which elſe muſt periſh at their charge; whoſe Examples are able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort all the Arguments of Irreligion upon its own breaſt, whoſe very countenance and behaviour is able to demonſtrate, far more effectually than all our faint breath, that <hi>'Tis not in vain to ſerve God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, This weak accompt I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the uſefulneſs of <hi>Religious Worſhip,</hi> hath no other deſire than to remove that ugly vizor, that hath disfigured, not only the Faces of the <hi>Votaries,</hi> but even that of <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, and made it look like a diſmal and <hi>chagrene</hi> thing; and ſo hath it diſguiſed its native lovelineſs, that ſome <hi>enjoyn</hi> it, moſt look upon it as a meer <hi>penance,</hi> and to be ſad and devout, to be religious and ghaſtly, are grown the ſame; ſo thoſe in the <hi>Text</hi> make the <hi>Service of God</hi> conſiſt in <hi>walking mournfully before him,</hi> which whether it relate to their <hi>gate, look, habit</hi> or <hi>temper,</hi> or <hi>Ezra</hi>'s <hi>faſting,</hi> 'twas nothing that God required of them; the <hi>Good God</hi> never intended his Service ſhould waſte any Mans ſpirits, damp their hearts, drein their eſtates, or diſturb the World; if any therefore be ſick, be poor, be diſpirited, or contentious, 'tis not this that hath made them ſo. There are indeed in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> ſome ſharp Medicines, and if theſe put Men
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42086:20"/>to pain and ſorrow, they are to blame their intemperance, that hath made them neceſſary, and to call in the hopes of health, to make them tolerable; and yet there is not any the leaſt bodily neceſſity, the meaneſt worldly advantage, no nor the vileſt luſt, but puts Men to more torment and ſlavery, forces them to bow, to watch, to pray, to kiſs the duſt, more than the moſt painful ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of the humbleſt Suppliant and Penitent, under the firſt and pureſt Diſcipline of the Church.</p>
            <p>Did <hi>God</hi> require ſome hard and heavy things of us,<note place="margin">Joſh. 9.23.</note> were our <hi>Service in the Church</hi> as tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as that of the <hi>Gibeonites in the Temple;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 18.28, 29.</note> or as cruel as that of <hi>Baal</hi>s <hi>Votaries,</hi> and to as little purpoſe; then might we ſay, as they do, (<hi>ch.</hi> 1.13.) <hi>What a wearineſs is it?</hi> But ſince He asks no more, than that we <hi>reſt from our labours,</hi> and <hi>come together into his preſence,</hi> that <hi>we worſhip, and fall down and kneel before the Lord our Maker,</hi> that <hi>we laud and love his Name,</hi> that <hi>we confeſs and forſake our ſins</hi> which have no other fruit but <hi>ſorrow</hi> and <hi>ſhame,</hi> and that <hi>we hear and obey his Laws</hi> that our Souls may live; let us never repine to give Him this <hi>reaſonable Service,</hi> which will ſo abundantly reward us, <hi>enrich our Souls with goodneſs, unite our hearts in love,</hi> and prepare us for the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42086:20"/>and joys of Angels and perfected Spirits,</hi> by the Merits of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Saviour: <hi>To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, Worſhip, and Obedience given, world without end.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
